howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show
[Music]
today's guest is Jill tarter hi hi Jill
Jill's an astronomer best known for her
work on the search for extraterrestrial
intelligence usually shortened to SETI
SETI an acronym will use a lot today so
remember set e equals search for
extraterrestrial intelligence
[Music]
Jill is chairman emeritus for SETI
research at the SETI Institute and was
the inspiration for the Judy foster
character in the movie contact based on
the novel by Carl Sagan Jill here on the
show we've often discussed the Fermi
paradox has actually become sort of a
mini feature maybe half my guests I've
asked them what are their views about
the Fermi paradox could you tell that
story for us a little bit how did it
become called the Fermi paradox and what
is it well it shouldn't be called the
Fermi paradox because there's no paradox
what it's shaped as is the supposition
that any advanced technological
civilization anywhere in the galaxy
would very quickly develop the
opportunity for interstellar travel and
they would therefore colonize the galaxy
no matter what model you use in times
that are short compared to the lifetime
of the galaxy which is ten billion years
but it says well they're not here and
therefore the conclusion is there never
could have been any time or any when
another technological civilization so
we're the first the problem with that
construct is that we can't say that
they're not here and I really don't mean
little green men deducting an ALICE off
the city streets but we actually have
searched even just our own solar system
so poorly that there's no way we could
rule out the fact that there might be a
small object stuffed with all kinds of
intelligence artificial
intelligence in our galaxy in our solar
system rather and we wouldn't have found
it and this name was with the radio
searches and the optical searches for
signals so poorly explored are our own
backyard that there's no way we can make
a definitive statement they're not here
when I was doing my research for this
episode I saw I read an analogy it might
have been attributed to you I don't
recall which said that all of our
searches to date are considerably less
than one glass of water taken out of the
oceans of the world
that's right it's actually pretty full
glass by now but yes just one glass no
surprise that you don't get a fish if
you pull a glass of water out of the
ocean so our audience has heard you know
lots of quite sophisticated takes on you
know why are they not here or why have
we not found them question yet and
obviously that's what you've made most
of your career how did you happen to
come to become involved with SETI search
well it was just a very fortunate
accident my first year in graduate
school at Berkeley we got our first
desktop computer now at that time it
took two people to get it onto your
desktop but it was a PDP 8s and there
was no programming language so you had
to program the whole thing in octal you
had to set all the ones and zeros and I
learned that skill in order to program a
spectrometer at an optical telescope the
university used for teaching and many
years later as I was getting towards the
end of my graduate career this computer
was given as a piece of surplus gear to
Professor Stuart Boyer who had a very
clever idea about piggybacking on the
university's 85 foot radio telescope in
order to do steady searches at the same
time that other astronomers were doing
more traditional radio astronomy it was
very clever
he just had no money to pull it off and
so he went begging and people began
giving
things such as this old computer and he
came to my office with a copy of the
cyclops report the results of a summer
study design workshop that was looking
at what you might do to detect
extraterrestrial intelligence if you had
unlimited funds and he gave me the
cyclops report as a recruiting document
wanted me to join his team so that i
could program this hold a computer for
him and that's exactly what happened i
mean i read that cyclops report and i
thought my goodness here i am just the
right time with just the right skills an
undergraduate degree in engineering and
a PhD in astrophysics and here's his
fantastic problem this question that
we've been asking ourselves forever
and I could do something to contribute
so I got hooked and I stayed out wow
that's so lucky did you know what I
think about the big questions in science
and that's something at the Santa Fe
Institute where I've been affiliated for
the last eighteen years so we try to do
what are the big questions in my own
ranking I put SETI question as number
two number one for you number one is why
does this universe exist and after that
I think SETI is number two and of the -
I think SETI is the more likely to be
accessible to an answer in a reasonable
time frame and a humanly potential level
of effort but I also think it has a
gigantic moral component which I often
don't see talked about is that what one
level if the galaxy and the universe is
relatively abundant in intelligent life
then that means we're one of many and
while we have a duty to protect
ourselves for our own purposes we
probably don't have a higher duty to the
universe itself however should it turn
out that we are alone and it's funny
when I was a 12 year old nerdy guy who
you know stumbled up on astronomy in the
Drake Equation and such must Ben Wright
knew at the time I said
of course there's got to be plenty of
intelligent species in our galaxy alone
let alone the universe but as I've done
more reading on it and I've thought
about it hard and my own learnings and
complexity science and information
theory it's at least possible to my mind
that we might be alone and if we are
that we have a huge moral duty to the
universe which is to bring the universe
to life I would say that life is
fundamentally more interesting than non
life and if after a very extensive SETI
say you know thousand years at ten
billion dollars a year we were to
conclude that there were no other life
in the universe it would seem to me that
the mission for Humanity ought to be
come to bring the universe to life so
that's why I think this is such a hugely
important question and yet when I was
researching your career and the whole
SETI field I was flabbergasted by what a
struggle it's been for even the most
inconsequential funding it's like it's
madness you know what do you have to say
about that well I think it is madness
it's been an incredible roller coaster
for all these decades we have now mr.
Milner
who's taking on responsibility for
searches in this decade which is great
but we always need more money in the
field and I think we should get back in
the federal domain as well so the thing
that I really enjoy having the
opportunity to do is talking to
audiences such as yours and getting to
think about these bigger questions
getting them to think about themselves
as compared to something else that's out
there and if I can get them to engage
seriously with the topic then it has the
effect of of trivializing the
differences among humans because
compared to something else out there
we're all the same and I think that
cosmic perspective isn't
randomly important over the coming
decades to help us manage the various
challenges we face with climate and
water and food production and these are
challenges that don't recognize national
boundaries we're going to have to solve
them globally and so if I can help other
humans have this larger point of view
this this cosmic perspective they think
that goes a long way to finding the
answers we need I hadn't thought of that
that's a very interesting perspective
and certainly particularly relevant in
our current time when it sort of seems
like tribalism is making a big comeback
unfortunately and having that distance
saying you know on the on the scale of
the cosmos the difference between a
Sunni and Shia is inconsequential on the
scale of the universe so why are you
slaughtering each other right let us
realize that we are all life on Earth is
probably very close cousins compared to
anything we're going to discover in
another tree of life elsewhere and
that's it's a wonderful perspective I
think that's a very very healthy idea to
put out into the world let's switch back
now to SETI science a little bit more
directly the Drake Equation has long
been the touchstone for thinking about
SETI could you take us through it and
maybe tell us the the points in the
Drake Equation and maybe even a little
bit about what we know about them sure
but let's start out with the fact that
the Drake Equation is actually a great
agenda for a meeting but you can't
calculate anything with it there's just
too many unknowns but Frank Drake when
holding a meeting on this topic way back
in 1961 did put together an agenda and
he thought about all of the factors the
things that you would have to understand
in order to try and estimate the number
of communicative civilizations that
could be out there in the Milky Way and
he started with the rate of star
formation because we think stars are
needed to have planets and then we
wanted he wanted to know the fraction of
stars that actually had planets
remember it's only been the last decade
or so that we know about planets around
other stars back then we had no clue and
then he asked well in a planetary system
what's the average number of planets
like the earth that could be habitable
and in in our solar system he would have
said three you know Morris Earth and
Venus might have been good ideas for for
life and then of those good planets what
fraction of them actually does life
begin on and of all the life starts what
fraction of those develop intelligence
and of the intelligent species out there
what fraction of them develop a culture
and a civilization and lastly how long
does that technological civilization
last because if civilizations arise
develop technology and do themselves in
or turn themselves off very quickly
there's not likely to be anybody that's
going to be close enough and Co temporal
with us that is around at the same time
in the ten billion year history of the
galaxy so he multiplied all those
factors together and put in his own
favorite numbers and came out with with
ten thousand and people have been
arguing about the numbers ever since a
couple of summers ago the folks over in
Oxford who loved Bayesian calculations
looked at all the literature on this
topic and said within the literature for
the fraction of planets that actually
life starts on the probability of
abiogenesis they said there were a
hundred and twenty factors of ten
difference in numbers that people
ascribed to that factor and in a sense
we have no idea and a long time ago
philip morris and told me he's a pioneer
one of the pioneers in SETI told me that
any topic where the error bars are in
the exponent is a topic that isn't going
to yield to theory it's one that's going
to have to be solved I've understood
observations
they are experimental II and I certainly
believe that's the case with SETI we can
sit on a mountaintop and stare at our
navels all we want you think about it
but what's gonna answer this question is
observation at least until we have more
data and you know and it's kind of a
bootstrap like as you pointed out
actually I laughed when I went back and
looked at the Drake Equation it was
clear that that must have been stated
when the steady state theory of the
universe was still in play the way he
talked about planetary formation I
thought was interesting if he had been
clearly in the absolutely Big Bang side
of the world he might not have stated it
quite that way and also as you pointed
out we had no clue about the number of
planets I remember from my elementary
school science books they were still
arguing did planets come from the the
disk around the star which case they
would be common or was it the result of
a very rare near collision between two
stars in which case planets would be
rare I think we now know that it's the
first that it was from the accretion
discs around the stars and that probably
essentially every star has planets so
that there's some real data the Kepler
spacecraft and the ground-based
observations in the last decade haven't
checked ensured us that there are more
planets than stars in the galaxy yep and
clearly on very much on the high side of
what people might have thought so that
starts to tune in the the Drake Equation
or a replacement for it and then think
about other things that we will be
learning in the next 20 years is
biogenesis exceedingly difficult or is
it relatively common we'll have a few
clues one when we get out to the outer
planets and their satellites we'll be
able to dip into Europa and some of the
other possible sources of life and if we
can find a completely different tree of
life than ours you know that probably
tells the spider Genesis isn't that hard
in Mars we may find the separate tree of
life though I got to say my guess is if
we find life or residues of life on Mars
it would not at all shock me for us to
have found
that our life actually started on Mars
and came here on a lucky hop but we do
have those kinds of items of data coming
up and then the next thing we have
coming up are the atmospheric studies of
the exoplanets right where we'll be able
to look at constituents of the gases in
the exoplanets and look for signs of
life and each of those will start to
bound some of this uncertainty right but
the the bio signatures search that
you're talking about in exoplanet
atmospheres is going to be very nuanced
there is no smoking gun that we've been
able to postulate yet and so it's going
to be very much a result that depends on
context the age of the stellar system
and the planetary system and the
location relative to the star and if you
think about the Earth's atmosphere early
in its history our Earth's atmosphere
was dominated by methane coming from
methanogens but then we had 2.4 billion
years ago this great oxygenation event
'ln blue-green algae figured out how to
do photosynthesis and produce oxygen as
a by-product and then we change the
atmosphere completely and so while there
was life on Earth in both of these
variants the atmospheric trace gases
were completely different so
understanding in context for the planets
evolution is going to be necessary and
very hard to do as we make the
spectroscopic searches for various trace
gases yep well and it'll drive you know
thinking about the theory of how the
earth evolved as well at the same time
as you point out you know to agree that
we can reason from our own experience as
a plan on how our atmosphere evolved
over you know 3.5 or 4 billion years we
may be may provide us some models which
would say that atmospheres that look
like this are probably biotic and the
atmospheres that look like that maybe
not for instance at least something I
read said that a mixture of oxygen and
methane within certain ratios may be a
pretty good indicator a pretty good
biome
well it's actually an extremely good
indicator of chemical disequilibrium and
on our own atmosphere it's a hundred
times out of equilibrium so what you'll
see methane and oxygen you'll see this
strange chemistry that's out of
equilibrium so something's forcing it
but is that something biology or geology
there are ways to get oxygen that are
abiotic right and we don't know the
limits of how much out of equilibrium
you can force something without the
presence of biology it's just something
you don't yet know do we have i any
ideas about the difficulty of saying for
instance once we have a substantial body
of atmospheric surveys let's say a
thousand and if we see the oxygen
methane combination being like all these
water zone planets we see it being
fairly common are any of these
geological mechanisms plausible enough
that they would be common across this
body of planets or or does the that's a
high frequency of that signal tell us
something different than a single
occurrence of that signal yeah well is
it telling you that that life is
everywhere or is it telling you that
it's geologically not too hard to to get
this thing disequilibrium I don't know
we don't know interesting because I must
say when I think about the ways that we
might be alone many of them do come to
the earlier stages of biology how how
hard was biogenesis or how and right
around the transition when we once a
converse amazing conversation I had with
Stewart Kaufman many years ago and we
talked about the fact that in
evolutionary theory if you don't have
high fidelity information transfer
between generations you run into
something called the error catastrophe
where the ability to build up structure
is very limited but once you get to high
fidelity information replication such as
we have in the DNA architecture of even
the most
of bacteria and archaea then evolution
can work and then yes or ask yourself
the question without high-fidelity
information how in the world did the
earliest RK or bacteria or whatever
their common ancestor was managed to
develop this rather complicated
machinery for duplicating DNA Egham mmm
quite a puzzle might have been really
really unlikely so you know that's one
of these things that is we learn more
about the origins of life maybe we can
strike that one off the table say nope
that wasn't that hard or we can say yep
that was extremely difficult or they are
you know the next one on my list is the
apparently only one time the creation of
eukaryotic cell you know where we where
a was it a bacteria absorbed in archaea
or the other way around one of them
became the cell one of them became the
mitochondria and that increased the
energy density of living cells by what a
factor of 10,000 something like that or
I guess the gross energy of a cell by
something like a factor of 10,000 if it
happened only once in four billion years
doesn't tell us much about whether it's
one in many many more years or what lynn
margulis isn't still around I mean she
had such a hard time getting the
scientific community to accept that
model so symbiosis is not something we
were prepared to take on lens word that
took a lot of hard and painful
operations on lens part two to get this
notion across and accepted as far as I
know now it's accepted by everybody yeah
yeah you know we do a lot of tracking of
genetic evolution through the model
mitochondrial DNA right as we want to go
down the maternal line and say alright
this is what the maternal ancestry look
like separate from the paternal ancestry
and well but far as I know it's just
taken as reality now by everybody
working in the field okay let's turn a
little bit from the science and the
Drake Equation to policy one of the
things
came across in my research was something
called the first SETI protocol basically
a protocol for what we do if we think we
have a signal and we are starting to
verify it etc because you tell us a
little bit about that sure that protocol
was written back in the 80s during the
height of the Cold War and it was
written under the auspices of the
International Academy of astronautics
which has had a standing committee on
SETI for many many decades and back then
some of us were concerned that our
colleagues in the Soviet Union who were
doing SETI searches might succeed in a
detection but be prevented from making
that information public and so we wrote
this protocol as a way of encouraging
everybody who was operating and doing
SETI searches to have kind of a standard
way of behaving given success and it
basically said you need to verify with
your own instruments that what you think
you found is what you think it is you
need to try and get independent
confirmation quietly without making a
big fuss so that you can guard against
intentional hoaxes and then you need to
tell the world right and at least for
the signatures of that protocol
signatories we agreed that we would not
broadcast a reply until there had been
some international consensus that we
should do so and a decision about who
would speak first and what would be sent
so totally idealistic completely
unenforceable but written with the best
of intentions and hopefully to give our
Soviet colleagues some backing when they
wanted to make an announcement if they
ever succeeded is this protocol still a
live letter in the SETI community I mean
our new young researchers aware of it
and
for their acculturation into the city
researcher culture yes it is it's being
updated the last time about five years
ago by the International Academy of
astronautics permanent Study Committee
and I think that many young people who
are joining the field get told about
this very early on you know that what
would I do if I got that signal oh my
gosh we've had a couple of false
positives over my career and it's just a
huge adrenaline high I can't even
imagine what it must be like a minute
because it's like as I said it's the
second greatest discovery possible and
you know oh my god is this it have you
personally been involved in one of the
strong false positives oh yes I'd I was
involved at Green Bank West Virginia
back in 1997-98 am I telling us that
story up oh that's the be hair-raising
for me at least yes well at around five
o'clock in the morning I detected a
signal and if you think about what it
might have looked like the spectrum
looked like a picket fence that is there
were narrowband signals strong and
separated by a particular spacing and
many of them so it really did look like
a picket fence on our waterfall display
I did everything I could think of I
pointed the telescope oh the the
beginning of the story actually starts a
few days before we always did our study
observing in project Phoenix with two
telescopes widely separated by hundreds
of miles then we did this because we
were looking for narrowband signals
which our technology produces quite a
lot of and the trick here was that if
you use two widely spaced telescopes to
observe a particular target and you saw
the signal in both of them
the signal would actually show up at a
different frequency and different drift
rate slightly in the two telescopes
because of the Earth's rotation there
would be a differential Doppler
signature well makes perfect sense yeah
it was a really good way to filter out
our own technology so lightning struck
the telescope the second telescope in
Georgia and we still had the hundred and
forty foot telescope and in Green Bank
West Virginia and we had time and so we
continued observing and all we could do
to try again
to discriminate against our own
technology was to look at the star and
then look off the star and if it's
really coming from the star then we
should see it when we look on and we
shouldn't see it when we look off anyway
because of a lightning strike we lost a
disk drive of the telescope at Georgia
it took FedEx a few days to get a new
one in there to repair it and we kept
using the telescope at the National
Radio Astronomy Observatory in Green
Bank 140 foot and we'd point at the
target and then we point off the target
and then we come back and look at the
target and we should see a signal that's
really coming from a distant source on
the sky when we looked at it and we it
should go away when we looked off the
star and so we did that with this signal
and every time I pointed at the target
the signal was there every time I
pointed the telescope away the signal
was gone
this looked like a really good bet and
we started doing all of the things that
we had planned like reloading software
to make sure that it somebody had not
put a signal into our software and I
woke up my colleague and we tracked that
star for another few hours until it's
said and the signal was always there
when we looked in the direction of the
star and never when we looked away
but we did notice that in fact the
Doppler shift and rift were appropriate
to a source that was rising to the
zenith rather than setting in the West
and so we knew that it really wasn't
coming from that distant target and at
this point we had also alerted our
colleagues in California and they had a
model or a copy of our observing system
and they were watching what we were
doing and they were very excited in fact
and so we all went off to dinner at
Green Bank having Duke having made this
discovery that it really wasn't a signal
from extraterrestrial intelligence and
we forgot to tell our California
colleagues so they stayed up until about
when the target rose again expecting to
see a signal and I had a lot of fence
building to do rebuilding to do when I
when I got back to California they were
not pleased at all and as soon as I saw
what the parameters of this signal were
I wrote some code to interrogate the
database that we keep on all signals
that are detected to ask the question
had we seen this signal structure before
coming from some different direction on
the sky that was a clever thing to do
but I was so excited I mean adrenaline
was really unbelievable that I didn't
take very much care in formatting my
output and so when I looked at the
output I missed the fact that indeed we
had seen this signal before from another
direction could saved ourselves a day of
excitement if I been careful and not so
excited that I screwed up anyway that
was for me that was probably the most
exciting false positive that we've had
it was actually a good proof that your
protocols well-designed right because
despite the fact there a couple of
errors in the process and bad luck of
having your second Observatory down you
still didn't put out a false
announcement which I would say it's a
sign that your processes were good
because that's a human
affairs especially catastrophic problems
often come when multiple things go wrong
simultaneously so here you had several
right you at least two and nonetheless
you protected yourself with a
well-designed protocol all right got
lucky yeah where you got lucky all right
already I'll take lucky luckily if you
have your choice of lucky or smart or
lucky go for lucky every dime yeah in
fact it was not completely kept quiet
and by accident I had been scheduled to
fly out back to California the noon on
the day that I found that signal in the
morning so it was too early in
California to call my husband and say
I'm gonna stay out here for a while more
so I called our administrative assistant
and left a voicemail for her saying that
I wasn't gonna be coming home that day
and would she'd please tell my husband
and then during the day and Ryan Carl
Sagan's will call to discuss something
with me and Chris said oh well she's
staying in Green Bank a little longer
and from there it went to somehow bill
brought at the New York Times who called
up our colleagues in California and said
hmm here there's something interesting
going on do you want to talk about it
and sastras tech told him well
no give us another 8 hours and then
we'll talk to you and he was good enough
to do that
while back 8 hours later and we had to
say sorry false alarm amazing how a tiny
signal was able to propagate out to the
New York Times but that's the way the
world Majan today with Twitter oh my
goodness even the slightest link would
likely get magnified a million times yes
that is why the protocol needs to be
updated in fact we took on an exercise
called revising the Rio scale so in 2000
Ivan Allen Laura and I gave a paper in
Rio de Janeiro hence the name Rio scale
and we tried to come up with a numerical
scheme on the order of 0 to 10 like a
Richter scale that one could assign a
potential single detect
so that there would be some easily
remembered way of saying how important
this was how impactful this particular
detection was and the zero in that scale
is really important because then that's
what you give a hoax and there were
there are many people who enjoy
publishing the fact that they have
detected signals and the evidence is
just not there so we did that in 2000
and then just last year we revised it in
lieu of the media and the way that we
communicate information today and so
it's now a website and you can take a
look at how people are ranking that
putative detection and how the detection
either becomes more crystallized and
confirmed or fades away because the
imminence just don't support it I'm
finding the rios scale on the SETI
League dot org website is that the best
place to check it out that's an easy
place to check it out yes so for our
listeners type in Rio scale and pick the
link that goes to City League org Jim
that's the original one I haven't
checked that's a new one they really
should search on Rio 2.0 in this world
of as you say the hyperactive media this
is all really important stuff because
there are lots of malicious people out
there who would get a big giggle out of
doing a false SETI alarm let's get back
to our topic list here binary stars
what's the current thinking about
whether they might be suitable for life
and/or advanced civilizations right well
if you remember Tatooine it's the system
from star wars double star system that
Luke Skywalker grew up on a planet
around that double star system we've
actually found planets around binary
stars and Lawrence Doyle from the SETI
Institute was the one to recognize the
first such star so
in the Kepler database it's interesting
there are two configurations that we
think might allow or habitable planets
around binary stars one is if the binary
stars are very close together and you
have an orbit maybe seven times or eight
times as big as the separation between
the stars so the planet would circle
both stars and the other configuration
is widely spaced binaries where you can
have a stable planetary orbit around one
of the stars and both cases seem to give
us at least in terms of simulations
habitable conditions and whether or not
they the planets that are around such
stars actually are inhabited that's our
next question interesting and when they
would still thought that perhaps a
majority of stars are in binary or more
star systems is that still the evidence
from astronomy okay that's important
next question how far away could we with
our current level of detection detect
Earth's intelligent emissions sadly not
very far certainly the television
leakage which people always point to and
say oh the aliens are gonna discover us
with howdy-doody not so far not even to
the nearest star but if you talk about
our strongest transmitter which is a two
megawatt radar of the Arecibo
Observatory so you've got two ten to the
six power transmissions and a gain of 10
to the seven so you've got a few times
10 to the 13 watts of power in that beam
that's detectable very far sort of
halfway to the the galaxy center and the
only problem is that beam is incredibly
narrow hey it's not a it's not a
spherical wave it's just that tiny
little cylindrical it's like a pin
cushion
yes so that's interesting how about is a
more powerful than TV a military radar
or something like that yes you can get a
few a few light-years so truthfully if
they are out there they haven't seen us
unless they have a lot better detectors
than we do which is of course possible
and actually it's probably probable
because most of the stars in our
neighborhood in the galaxies are about a
billion years older than the Sun so had
a head start quite possibly and you know
a technology so we don't know they're
kind of two models for technological
growth one is the sort of s-curve that
we see in all sorts of biological and
engineered systems where you have
nothing and then you get an exponential
rise and then you saturate some resource
so your growth turns over and then the
other is you have nothing and you start
an exponential rise and it just keeps
going we don't know what the future will
be for technology whether we use up some
particular resource whether we decide to
turn inwards the way the Chinese did by
burning their ships on the beaches and
not and ceasing from the exploration
that they have been doing we just don't
know but in any case the probability is
highest that you will find that
technology in an old face rather than at
their early stages so it's not unwise to
expect some more advanced technology
than we have indeed Arthur Clarke had
three laws the first one when an elderly
Scientists tells you something is
possible he's almost certainly correct
when he tells you something's impossible
he's almost certainly incorrect
the second law is the only way to
understand what's possible is to push
beyond into the impossible and the third
is any sufficiently advanced technology
would be indistinguishable from magic
last one I really like and you know
again it might be one of the conditions
where they're there but we just can't
see them because the way they
communicate from our perspective is
magical we can't even imagine maybe they
manipulate gravity waves or something
right
and so there's been recently a variant
of that third law Karl Schroeder of
philosopher environmentalist
said that any sufficiently advanced
technology will be indistinguishable
from nature
there was actually a paper written by
David Wolper tupple of guys that
indicated that the most efficient
communication system using
electromagnetism it was very likely to
look like noise right that it's so
sophisticated and so compressed that it
was not a beacon to be found we may well
mistake it for nature that's right and
and I think a lot of us are excited at
the moment about putting some neural
networks into our signal detection
programs so that instead of us telling
the machines to look for a particular
type of signal one that we think is
obviously engineered and the nature
doesn't produce we're hoping that with
trained neural networks we can allow the
machine to tell us whether there's
something other than noise in the data
that would be a very good use of machine
learning I mean machine learning is
perfect for that kind of problem where
you're looking for statistical anomalies
that irrespective of whether humans can
imagine them or not which is actually
very similar to how a AI is evolving
that's an area that I follow very
closely and you know good old-fashioned
AI basically a bazillion if-then
statements that were limited by how
smart the graduate students were now we
have machine learning that is able to
find things that no infinite army of
graduate students would have ever found
by doing inferences from unbelievably
large data sets seems to be a very good
fit for the SETI program so I would
definitely think that makes a lot of
sense another science question there's
been a lot of development the last 20
years around extremophiles forms of life
on Earth that have been discovered in
unbelievably hostile environments and
that would seem to speak towards
at least say something about maybe the
range for which life could exist is
wider than we think
absolutely so over my career the
exoplanets and the extremophiles have
been the two real huge game changers and
you know we say they live in hostile
environments but it's only hostile to us
they've evolved to be fat dumb and happy
in those environments and it's just a
surprise to us you know we we have this
wrong attitude we talk about the ascent
of man and we talk about humans being
the pinnacle of evolution well that's a
perspective that just isn't borne out by
nature we are just one little trick and
there is an amazing amazing abundance of
life in environments that when I was a
student I was told were sterile you know
and they've never been sterile we just
haven't been open-minded enough to
define them I understand things like
battery acid you know deep deep deep
under the Earth's surface just an
amazingly harsh environment that's right
and some of these like radiodurans
incredible tolerance to very high
temperatures and desiccation it actually
has ways of repairing its DNA that are
not something that humans do and so one
of the things that's been fun at the
SETI Institute is that we now have
researchers from the medical profession
coming along on expeditions to study
extremophiles sites because they're
wondering what they can learn that might
be beneficial to human health by
studying these extremophiles very
interesting as you say it's another one
that's I would say argued in favor of
SETI extremophiles and as you say lots
of planets too good things probably on
the equation though we're still out in
deep than twiddling with the exponents
so if we still don't know
next question a lot of your work in
particular has been around signals but
there is also other possible ways to the
tech savvy or at least past SETI what
people might call artifacts you know a
member of the stories about tabbies star
or the possibility of Dyson rings or
Dyson shells I could tell us a little
bit more about that
well SETI first of all is a misnomer and
always has been because we don't know
how to directly detect intelligence what
we're doing is using technology as a
proxy and if we find the technology we
are going to infer the presence of
intelligent technologists at least at
some point in time so we've begun using
a term that's techno signatures it
parallels the bio signature work looking
for evidence of any kind of life
microbes we want to look for the
mathematicians so we're looking for
techno signatures anything that would be
a change in the environment in a way
that you could sense over interstellar
distances so the Dyson Sphere discussion
or mega-structure discussion that was
going on with respect to tabby star is
one such techno signature and what we're
doing is we're we're thinking about the
new telescopes that are going to be
coming online in the next decade or so
for astronomical research and we're
thinking okay what might those
telescopes see that would be an
indication of somebody else's technology
so an example that I like to talk about
is the Trappist one system this this is
a system with at least seven planets
orbiting a little red dwarf star and
their orbits are so tight that the whole
system would fit within the orbit of
mercury around our star but even though
the orbits are tight they are still at
different distances from their host star
and therefore should have different
equilibrium temperatures but what if we
took a look at that system with some of
these
instruments that we'll have in the
future and discovered that three of them
were identical even though they're at
different distances from their star they
had the same equilibrium temperature
they had the same kind of chemical
structures in their atmospheres um to me
that would be suggestive of somebody
else's engineering on a very large scale
and so that would be a technical
signature very clever I like that a lot
actually and again if you only have a
small number of systems you look at well
who the hell knows but if you have a
bunch of them and have a bunch of them
with that signature then you're starting
to think about maybe we have a
high-frequency pattern here on the other
hand one of our previous guests on the
Jim Rutte show Robin Hanson who's I
would say a sette pessimist his argument
was that inevitably
any advanced really advanced
civilization ought to show a giant shift
of its energy from its star to the
infrared as it starts to use more and
more of its star's energy and yet he
argues and I will say he's an economist
and a raconteur not a physical scientist
he claims that we should have already
seen such large scale red shifts if
there were a lot of advanced
civilizations even in other galaxies how
would you respond to that well indeed
Jason Wright and his colleagues at Penn
State University have done exactly such
a search right they've used the data
from the wise infrared spacecraft that
surveyed the entire sky and they have
looked first of all for technology on a
huge scale so-called Kardashev three
type civilizations which are able to
manipulate the total energy output of
their galaxy and they've looked for
these infrared signatures from galaxies
that was the easy part of the search
then now they are looking at stellar
sources and looking for infrared
excesses in stars that's a lot harder
because of the confusion limit in the
observations but it's it's
something that's been thought of and in
fact people are trying to do it glad to
see that they're Pro bring on all these
theories and now we've kind of talked
about the past and the theoretical basis
etc what's really going on right now one
of the big efforts in SETI right now I
know there's you know the out you have
your Allen telescope array from the SETI
Institute and then the guys that break
through or buying time on radio
telescopes you know tell us about some
of the projects they're actually ongoing
as we speak
well the breakthrough listen team at
Berkeley is renting time Green Bank in
West Virginia and the the new telescope
their 100 meter telescope they are also
renting time Parkes New South Wales and
they are looking at building
instrumentation and backends for new
telescope called meerkat in South Africa
ultimately me hope this equipment will
be on the Square Kilometre Array when
that gets built
they have memoranda of understanding
with the Chinese for instrumenting the
fast the new radio telescope in China
they are also looking towards joggled
Bank in the UK and they will be
increasing their efforts getting there
very beautiful back in equipment on to
telescopes around the world we also have
some optical SETI projects and
particular one that I'm I'm really
excited about as being done at the SETI
Institute it's called laser SETI and the
idea here is that with 12 sites around
the world and eight cameras at each site
we could be looking for optical flashes
optical SETI on all the sky all the time
and if you're looking for something
transient this is what you want to do we
knew that back in 2000 when we wrote the
SETI 2020 report that said what we
should be doing for the next 20 years
and looking for transients looking at
all the sky all the time
as many different frequencies as we
could with something that we realized we
should be doing but until now we have
not had the technological capability to
do so so this will be the first truly
all-sky all the time
Observatory for SETI and the first
cameras have been installed now at the
Robert Ferguson Observatory up in Sonoma
County the next one will go to Holly
Aquila in Hawaii then there's another
optical SETI program that is being
worked on Pano's NE and the idea here is
if you remember the buckminster fuller
domes
well you fill each of those segments on
a dome with a big plastic Rennell lens
and then you focus a large piece of the
sky on a small infrared detector so you
build a telescope that has something
like a hundred and twenty different
beams so looks at a number of square
degrees I think it's hmm I don't have my
notes in front of me I think it's 8,000
square degrees and does this same sort
of observing for flashes and then you
build a second one of these a little bit
away right that's that's sounding
familiar from Project Phoenix so that
you can get confirmation of anything
that's detected I mean you see something
flash once and well gee what was it was
it our instrumentation or was that
something really there but if you have a
second one of these you can get
confirmation and I'm excited to see that
go forward and then we're thinking about
gee all of these wonderful new
telescopes the TMT that will be built
somewhere
the LSST the very large optical
telescope being built by europe and
perhaps in the radio the next-generation
VLA and the Square Kilometre Array and
so we've been thinking about how we can
get signal processing in parallel with
these telescopes how we can use them to
do SETI at the same time that radio
astronomy is being done
and so something is happening right now
at the Very Large Array the radio
telescope in the southwest and we are
essentially building a spigot that can
take data being observed by anyone for
any purposes and that spigot makes the
data available to SETI detectors so the
breakthrough team will be building a
back-end to swallow data from that
spigot so they can be on the air
essentially all the time and this goes
back to the first project I ever did
with Stu Boyer serendipity which is
saying we can't decide where the
telescope is going to point or what
frequency it's going to observe at but
it will give us a whole lot of time on
the sky and you know that some level we
don't really know where to look anyway
so we might as well just look where the
astronomers are looking and so this
back-end device for the VLA should be up
and running in a year or two and that's
gonna be an exciting opportunity because
that's a very large telescope and of
course you have Moore's law working for
us now back when your PD PAP would have
had no hope to process all that data but
today with many generations of Moore's
law increasing the amount of transistors
and driving the costs down
we have almost ubiquitous computer
processing to do things like machine
learning on all this data yes thank you
guard anymore
absolutely okay let's move on to the
next topic and this is where we get into
some controversy
Meddy the idea that perhaps while we
continue to listen we ought to step up
and broadcast in fact my next guest on
the gym rat show David Brin has very
strong views about Medi I wonder what
your thoughts are on whether we should
be in the for you know first tell the
audience what it means to be
broadcasting versus listening and if you
have views on whether that's a good idea
or not well I do there are a little less
extreme than than David's but Medi is
this idea of mess
jeanny extraterrestrial intelligence
that if everybody is listening and no
one is transmitting that's not going to
work so we should step up to the plate
and transmit to allow other advanced
civilizations to know that we're here
and interested in community and my
problem with that is that we barely
managed as a species to get through two
year plans very occasionally we get
through a five-year plan intact but
we're not set up to tackle ten thousand
year plans and the thing about
transmitting is if it's going to make
any difference
you have to start and not stop because
if you transmit for five minutes your
signals gonna go whipping by your target
in five minutes and they would have to
be looking at you exactly the right time
with exactly the right tools to catch
that signal and then they're going to be
a little bit wary about whether that one
shot was really something or something
they can't explain and so I think that
transmitting is a long-term project and
we're just not grown-up enough yet as a
technological civilization to do that
when we are I think we ought to take on
the role of transmitting I I often think
that perhaps and again it's just my
thoughts perhaps the distribution of
intelligent technological civilization
ages is bimodal there are a lot of
technical civilizations that pop up and
don't manage to last very long but there
are some that do make it through any
kind of a filter to on an old age and I
wonder if transmissions the detection of
a transmission from another
technological civilization it might not
be the distinguishing characteristic
about whether you tunnel through from
the very young and make it to be an old
civilization so I think there is
potentially as we become old and stable
there might be an onus on us to help
others get there too although we seem to
be a very long way from old ores
truthfully the modern world's only 400
years old and I put the start of
modernism as 1625 right and so on the
scale of the universe we are not an old
Society at all we're not even an infant
or hardly right we're still a fetus so I
think at this stage in our development
we do the easier thing first which is
listen are you concerned about some of
the you know precautionary principle
type arguments against transmitting you
know the David Brenner Stephen Hawking
ideas that hey maybe the universe has or
the galaxy is full of predators and it
would be damn stupid for us to announce
our presence well why does that worry us
it worries us because we think they
might show up on our doorstep and have
us for lunch right but think about it if
they can get here we can't get there but
if they can get here then their
technology is a lot more advanced than
ours they probably already know about
our existence because of the ways that
we use the electromagnetic spectrum and
they're gonna write the rules one way or
another and I actually think unlike
Stephen Hawking I actually think that
there might not be any reason to have
fears about this happening because they
can get here then they are truly an
advanced technological civilization and
I think perhaps the stability that that
age implies would argue that they have
had to outgrow the really ignatius
tendencies that they might have had
earlier in their evolution because if
they haven't I don't think they can
become old and advanced so it's kind of
the steven pinker kinder and gentler
argument of cultural evolution that's
certainly a hopeful way to think about
it and if we were to find such a
civilization the things we could learn
could be unbelievably huge one would
think you know civilization a billion
years older than ours able to
navigate between the stars it be very
surprising if we didn't have something
to learn from a civilization like that
agreed and we probably don't have a lot
to offer them except our uniqueness as a
species so that's my philosophy but I'm
an optimist by Nature
yeah I wonder but very interesting here
what David Brin has to say on Monday
about this but as I understand he has
other views so that's that's why we do
the show get all kinds of different
views out there let's move on again a
little bit I read a recent paper may
even have been in draft by someone named
Jason Wright and by his calculation the
federal government is currently spending
260 thousand that's thousand people per
year on SETI I'm going that's nuts you
know that is nuts
what is the problem with our science
that to address the second biggest
question in science and the and the
biggest one that's accessible at this
point in time that we would be spending
something considerably less than the
bagel budget for one small agency to
answer this question do you have any
idea what is it about SETI that is
repugnant to federal funding well my
opinion and again it is an opinion and I
concur with Jason's numbers is that it's
fundamentalist religion there is an
element of our Congress whose
constituents think that we on earth have
a unique and special relationship with
Jesus Christ and that is not consistent
with other technological civilizations
all around the place
so when you ask the world's major
religions about the question of life
beyond Earth they have no problem with
fitting this into their dogma but when
it comes to the fundamentalist Christian
religions in this country some of them
do you find this extremely upsetting and
that reflects on their representatives
we think there's enough pressure just
from that you know the kind of fringe
early Earth
young earth people to be able to
actually prevent the allocation of da
appropriate level of funding
yes well the SETI NASA SETI project was
cancelled by one senator it was done in
such a harsh and deliberately punitive
fashion that you know said he became the
four-letter S word that you couldn't say
at headquarters for well since 1993 and
we're now talking again about the
potential of searching for techno
signatures as well as bio signatures and
the astrobiology program and we're
looking at trying to get back into
federal funding but I don't know if
we're going to be successful as I said
been a roller coaster drives me crazy to
even think about this right if I were
the philosopher King you know I'd
allocate at least two billion dollars a
year to SETI something on the order of
ten percent of the NASA budget why
wouldn't you I can take the other side
and say that you wouldn't allocate huge
amounts of money you would allocate
money in a way that is continuous into
the long future the point is we may be
doing an incredibly fabulous job at
exactly the wrong thing we may not yet
have invented or discovered the
appropriate technology for interstellar
communication so we ought to fund this
in a way that is dependable and
consistent something like an endowment
at a reasonable level but not a huge
level because when you talk to young
people and you try and encourage them to
come into the field with all their new
ideas and talents it's a bit fringy but
if you have to say to them at the same
time well not only is this a bit off the
mainstream but I may not be able to
cover your salary next month that
becomes a real challenge and we do want
the best and brightest of the young
scientists and engineers coming in to
enhance and improve this field but we
need to be able to say and yes you can
raise a family - yep absolutely if if
you were the philosopher king of
America what would you think is a
reasonable expenditure raid odds I mean
maybe even an unreasonably aggressive
but not insane level to spend on Ceti
per year we've taken a look at that
question and seeing what we can what we
know is in the pipeline what might be
coming down yeah I would you know I
would be doing twenty to thirty million
dollars a year unbelievably tiny dollars
on the scale of our federal budget and a
few religious nuts are preventing this
from happening this really annoys me
it's not been an easy ride and I may be
wrong that may not be why it was
terminated but it certainly we got
indications that that's what senator
Bryan was about
well you certainly were at the center of
it more than any other human on earth I
mean you are one of my great heroes for
having dedicated your life to this
project which I believe to be of the
utmost importance and yet has been not
given anything like the support and
respect that it deserves so I will take
your word for that as a very likely
possibility of why this has been not
funded appropriately 20 million dollars
people my listeners out there call your
Congressman call your senators tell them
that a tiny amount of money probably the
cost of three flashlights and a hammer
for the Pentagon we could have a program
that would make Jill tarter happy for
SETI to answer the second biggest
scientific question that humanity
confronts this is just driving me mad
that this is not happening so maybe our
audience can help make this happen
I love to be next year and the year
after that and the year after that etc
make it a long-term commitment 100 year
commitment right I've seen in some of
the things I research that you've
proposed thinking about that way you
know over a hundred years we could look
X light-years out why number of stars
and then now we can have these other
technologies you know laser SETI vs.
artifact looking versus you know radio
frequency listening and one could you
know essentially build a series of of
cells and fill them out over a hundred
years right and at that point we can say
alright this is what we've learned
here's our Bayesian here's our new
Bayesian right here's our prior here's
what we found what do we think now based
on a hundred years or the research and
again a hundred years is nothing in
astronomical time it would take us a
hundred thousand years it's still a
search worth doing it seems to me oh I'm
in I agree with you I'm a little bit of
a nut on this this is why we've talked
about the Fermi paradox and SETI and
half of my episodes I just think this is
one of the most important things out
there so my final question which is your
bottom line after being the leading
researcher in the world on this field
for most of your adult life I would ask
you to give me your best guess and
underlined guess this is not binding we
know we don't know the answer what do
you think about intelligent life in the
universe I'm not gonna answer your
question Jim because I don't have an
answer I think we can get an answer but
doing this experiments right if I told
you anything it would be religion and
not science right let's let's actually
do the exploration I think I spent my
entire career trying to convert the verb
to believe into the verb to explore I
think that's the proper thing to do you
are absolutely right I'm almost
embarrassed from for asking you that
question cuz you just gave me the answer
I should have known before I even asked
it well thank you Jill this has been
frankly an honor to talk to one of my
great heroes and also I hope extremely
enlightening and educational for our
audience well thank you very much for
having me I've enjoyed the conversation
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
Stanton media lab music by Tom Muller at
modern space music calm
[Music]